Christian Astudillo

20 Stallion Street Mechanicsburg PA 17050| (610) 203-2522 | cdastudillo@outlook.com | www.linkedin.com/in/christianastudillo

SUMMARY

Experienced problem-solver with consulting experience utilizing various research methodologies and analytic techniques in a wide range of applications (e.g., BHRS, Higher Education, Government Logistics, Health Insurance). **Developed an understanding of the following areas**:

Predictive Analytics• Research Design• Data Analysis and Reporting• Advanced Statistics• Program Evaluation•Human Factors• Presenting Research• Client Interaction• Public Speaking• Critical Thinking• Data Collection• Data Cleaning• Survey Development• Data Visualization• Group Dynamics• Spreadsheet Development• Technical Writing• IBM SPSS• Microsoft Works• Visual Basic • Basic HTML Coding •SQL •Microsoft Word •Microsoft Excel •Microsoft PowerPoint •Adobe Live Cycle •QMF •SAS Enterprise Guide •VBA •R programming•Python•Power BI•Tableau

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

POPULATION HEALTH DATA SCIENCE MANAGER | CAPITAL BLUECROSS, HARRISBURG, PA | AUGUST 2019 - CURRENT

- Provide support to health system groups by running ad-hoc data requests
- Developed the HBA1c Report utilizing **data mining techniques to identify opportunities** for HEDIS gap closures thus **increasing HEDIS rates**
- Developed the Avoidable Emergency Department dashboard for **trend comparisons** and identification of members who are frequently using it
- Conduct **statistical testing** on marketing campaigns to determine the impact on the HEDIS metrics in order to determine 2020 measure focus when developing the campaigns
- Created visual representation utilizing R to display top 10 providers and physicians per health system group based on a weighted score ranking system
- Created interim HEDIS benchmarks in SAS utilizing historical data trends for each HEDIS measure
- Attempted to build logistic regression models to predict the likelihood of a member being compliant for a HEDIS measure
- Developed a top 5 facility usage by health system by normalizing the data and ranking facility based on standard deviations
- Conduct statistical testing on multiple programs and vendors to determine the impact on ROI
- Constantly looking for ways to utilize R for data mining, data cleaning, and data analysis.
- Developed a Year over Year **Power BI dashboard** to inform external partners on Covid Impact for Hedis Metrics
- Developed a Population Assessment analysis utilizing **Tableau** to present significant trends and insights
- Developed a Covid 19 Vaccine list to identify members eligible for the vaccine using data mining techniques to meet specific medical diagnosis criteria
- Analyzed program effectiveness for a vendor utilizing statistical modeling and utilized a **random forest model** to determine predictors for compliance on HbA1c metrics

BUSINESS DATA ANALYST | UNITY TECH, NEW CUMBERLAND, PA | FEBRUARY 2018 - AUGUST 2019

• Participate in developing solutions to problems using applied research methodologies and statistical analysis techniques (Proper usage of statistical tests)

- Created interactive PDF test sheets using Adobe Live Cycle for more efficient data collection thus reducing time spent from previous data collection methods, up to 50 percent
- Utilize Microsoft Excel to import data collected and transform the data for analysis and visual reporting
- Utilize Microsoft Access to query data for further inspection and to maintain large data sets
- Utilize Data Analysis Tool Pack for more advanced statistical analyses (correlations, crosstabs, ANOVAS etc.)
- Pull large amount of Data using IBM QMF program and writing complex SQL syntax to reduce processing time
- Data Analyst Lead for transaction tracing of different NIINs utilizing code developed from QMF for Ernst & Young Audit and successfully reduced processing and reporting time by roughly 60 percent
- Utilize VBA coding in order to create macros to automate complicated processes thus increasing processing time and efficiency
- Utilize SAS programming on datasets that are not supported in Excel for data mining, data manipulation, data cleaning, and data analysis.
- Lead Analyst for DLA Distribution 100 Percent Inventory Progress. **Developed a Semi-Automated flow** using SAS programs, Access queries, and Excel formulas to create a weekly progress tracker
- Maintain and modify previous existing SAS Programs to develop CRM metrics
- Developed an assessment on SQL knowledge to identify the team's areas to focus on. In the process of creating a DLA Distribution SQL specific tutorial
- **Developed a forecasting tool to predict** the amount of material (-/+ 5 confidence intervals) within all 25 Distribution centers for the following month. The tool is used to plan ahead and schedule workload accordingly to reduce overstaffing and duplicated work. This has allowed DLA **to save expenses in man hours**
- **Created an interactive access database utilizing VBA** that will be used among DLA Enterprise for the Floor to Book 2 percent program. This will allow DLA Distribution HQ to analyze controls in a timely manner
- Meet deadlines with alternative products for the government leads to choose from
- Create dynamic dashboards to visualize trends and progress among different DLA areas (STO ISDRs, PListing errors, CA Dispatch Report errors, DSS ATR D8A/D9A counts etc.)
- Ability to work independently for long periods of time as well as interpret, understand, and use various statistical models and techniques
- Willingness to work in group dynamics and mentor coworkers with SQL and Advanced Statistics
- Constantly finding methods to automate tasks and improve workflow

BEHAVIOR SPECIALIST CONSULTANT | LAUREL LIFE, CHAMBERSBURG & CARLISLE, PA | JUNE 2017 - FEBRUARY 2018

- **Ensured client received proper intervention** using the data collected from a functional behavior analysis
- Helped **decrease problem behaviors** by researching and documenting methods previously used for other clients
- Worked alongside team members to determine best course of action and successful intervention
- Utilized Microsoft Excel to import data collected and create pivot tables for comparison of data trends
- Utilized Microsoft Word to present effective data visualization on behavior trends with the client's team
- First Clinician to utilize SPSS for more advanced statistical measures on the data collected

RESEARCH ASSISTANT | SHIPPENSBURG UNIVERSITY, SHIPPENSBURG, PA | SEPTEMBER 2014 - MAY 2015

- Successfully found data significance between athletes in group sports by transforming raw unstructured data into meaningful variables for comparison
- Effectively led a small team of peers to collect data using email, word of mouth, and social media platforms
- **Achieved a 10% participant increase** by implementing an incentive program.
- Collaborated with a team and used Microsoft Excel to clean up raw unstructured data imported Via SurveyMonkey
- Analyzed data pools consisting of over 5000 entries using IBM SPSS
- Utilized IBM SPSS to run different analyses (Correlations, ANOVAS, MANOVAS, Regression etc.) on appropriate variables

ADDITIONAL EXPERIENCE

ORIENTATION LEADER | SHIPPENSBURG UNIVERSITY, SHIPPENSBURG, PA | JUNE 2013 - FEBRUARY 2015

- Successfully multitasked to serve more than one student at a time and provided a pleasant orientation experience
- Build strong connections with incoming students to ensure that they recognized a familiar face when they attended the university in the fall
- Collected data for program evaluation from the students on what to improve for the next orientation session
- Analyzed data and presented it to the director for further brainstorming ideas
- Worked alongside other orientation leaders to handle difficult situations

EDUCATION

BA PSYCHOLOGY | MAY 2015 | SHIPPENSBURG UNIVERSITY

Cum Laude (GPA: 3.5, Psychology GPA: 3.8)

Relevant Coursework

- PSY 105 Research & Design Behavior Science I
- PSY 205 Research & Design Behavior Science II
- PSY 305 Applied Research & Methodologies
- CSC 180 Microcomputer Basic
- PSY 374 Advanced Research I
- MAT 117 Applied Statistics
- PSY 375 Advanced Research II

MS PSYCHOLOGICAL SCIENCE | MAY 2017 | SHIPPENSBURG UNIVERSITY

General/Comprehensive Track (GPA: 3.5)

Relevant Coursework

- PSY 500 Advanced Research & Design Statistics I
- PSY 501 Advanced Research & Design Statistics II
- PSY 570 Seminar Cognitive Science
- PSY 512 Theories of Learning

MS DATA SCIENCE | OCTOBER 2021 - CURRENT | EASTERN UNIVERSITY

General/Comprehensive Track (GPA: 4.0)